Chapter 105. Does the whale's magnitude diminish? Will he perish?
In as much then as this Leviathan comes floundering down upon us from the
headwaters of the eternities, it may be fitly inquired whether in the long
course of his generations, he has not degenerated from the original bulk of
his sires. But upon investigation, we find that not only are the whales of the
present day superior in magnitude to those whose fossil remains are found in
the tertiary system, embracing a distinct geological period prior to man.
But of the whales found in that tertiary system, those belonging to its latter
formations exceed in size those of its earlier ones.
Of all the pre-atomite whales yet exumed, by far the largest is the
Alabama one mentioned in the last chapter, and that was less than 70 ft in
length in the skeleton. Whereas we have already seen that the tape measure gives
72 ft for the skeleton of a largesized modern whale. And I have heard on
whaleman's authority that sperm whales have been captured near 100 ft long at
the time of capture.
But may it not be that while the whales of the present hour are an advance in
magnitude upon those of all previous geological periods, may it not be that
since Adam's time they have degenerated.
Assuredly we must conclude so if we are to credit the accounts of such gentlemen
as Plenny and the ancient naturalists generally for Plenny tells us of whales
that embraced acres of living bulk and Aldraandis of others which measured 800
ft in length rope walks and temps tunnels of whales and even in the days
of banks and slander cooks naturalists we find a Danish member of the academy
of sciences setting down certain Iceland whales raiden ciser or wrinkled bellies
at 120 yards that is 360 ft and lassipede the French naturalist in his
elaborate history of whales in the very beginning of his work page three sets
down the right whale at 100 m 328 ft and this work was published so late as AD
1825 but will any whaleman believe these stories? No. The whale of today is as
big as his ancestors in Plenny's times.
And if ever I go where Plenny is, I a whaleman more than he was, will make
bold to tell him so, because I cannot understand how it is, that while the
Egyptian mummies that were buried thousands of years before even Plenny
was born do not measure so much in their coffins as a modern Kuckian in his
socks, and while the cattle and other animals sculptured on the oldest
Egyptian and Nineveh tablets by the relative proportions in which they are
drawn, just as plainly prove that the hybrid, stall-fed, prized cattle of
Smithfield, not only equal, but far exceed in magnitude the fattest of
Pharaoh's fat kind. In the face of all this, I will not admit that of all
animals the whale alone should have degenerated.
But still another inquiry remains, one often agitated by the more recondite Nantucketers,
whether owing to the almost omniscient lookouts at the mast heads of the whale
ships, now penetrating even through bearing straits, and into the remotest
secret drawers and lockers of the world, and the thousand harpoons and lances
darted along all continental coasts. The moot point is whether Leviathan can long
endure so wide a chase and so remorseless a havoc, whether he must not
at last be exterminated from the waters and the last whale like the last man
smoke his last pipe and then himself evaporate in the final puff.
Comparing the humped herds of whales with the humped herds of buffalo, which
not 40 years ago overspread by tens of thousands, the prairies of Illinois and
Missouri, and shook their iron manes, and scowlled with their thunderclotted
brows upon the sights of populous river capitals, where now the polite broker
sells you land at a dollar an inch. In such a comparison, an irresistible
argument would seem furnished to show that the hunted whale cannot now escape speedy extinction.
But you must look at this matter in every light, though so short a period
ago, not a good lifetime, the census of the buffalo in Illinois exceeded the
census of men now in London. And though at the present day not one horn or hoof
of them remains in all that region, and though the cause of this wondrous
extermination was the spear of man, yet the far different nature of the whale
hunt per perempily forbids so in glorious an end to the Leviathan.
40 men in one ship hunting these sperm whales for 48 months think that they
have done extremely well and thank God if at last they carry home the oil of 40
fish. Whereas in the days of the old Canadian and Indian hunters and trappers
of the west when the far west in whose sunset suns still rise was a wilderness
and a virgin. The same number of moccasin men for the same number of
months mounted on horse instead of sailing in ships would have slain not 40
but 40,000 and more buffaloos, a fact that if need were could be statistically stated.
Nor considered a right does it seem any argument in favor of the gradual
extinction of the sperm whale for example that in former years the latter
part of the last century say these Leviathans in small pods were
encountered much oftener than at present and in consequence the voyages were not
so prolonged and were also much more remunerative because as has been
elsewhere noticed those whales influenced by some views to safety
now swim the seas in immense caravans, so that to a large degree these
scattered solitaries, yolks, and pods, and schools of other days are now
aggregated into vast but widely separated, unfrequent armies, that is
all. And equally facious seems the conceit that because the so-called whale
bone whales no longer haunt many grounds in former years abounding with them,
hence that species also is declining, for they are only being driven from
Promontory to Cape. And if one coast is no longer enlivened with their jets,
then be sure some other and remoter strand has been very recently startled
by the unfamiliar spectacle.
Furthermore, concerning these last mentioned Leviathans, they have two firm
fortresses, which in all human probability will forever remain
impregnable. And as upon the invasion of their valleys, the frosty Swiss have
retreated to their mountains, so hunted from the savas and glades of the middle
seas, the whale bone whales can at last resort to their polar citadels, and
diving under the ultimate glassy barriers and walls there, come up among
icy fields and flows, and in a charmed circle of everlasting December, bid
defiance to all pursuit from man.
But as perhaps 50 of these whalebone whales are harpooned for one cashelo,
some philosophers of the folk have concluded that this positive havoc has
already very seriously diminished their battalions. But though for some time
past a number of these whales, not less than 13,000, have been annually slain on
the Northwest Coast by the Americans alone, yet there are considerations
which render even this circumstance of little or no account as an opposing
argument in this matter.
Natural as it is to be somewhat incredulous concerning the populousness
of the more enormous creatures of the globe, yet what shall we say to Hartto,
the historian of Goa, when he tells us that at one hunting the king ofSiam took
4,000 elephants, that in those regions elephants are as numerous as droves of
cattle in the temperate clims. And there seems no reason to doubt that if these
elephants, which have now been hunted for thousands of years by Semiramis, by
Porus, by Hannibal, and by all the successive monarchs of the east, if they
still survive there in great numbers, much more may the great whale outlast
all hunting, since he has a pasture to expatiate in, which is precisely twice
as large as all Asia, both Americas, Europe, and Africa, New Holland, and all
the isles of the sea combined.
Moreover, we are to consider that from the presumed great longevity of whales,
they're probably attaining an age of a century or more. Therefore, at any one
period of time, several distinct adult generations must be contemporary.
And what that is, we may soon gain some idea of by imagining all the graveyards,
cemeteries, and family vaults of creation, yielding up the live bodies of
all the men, women, and children who were alive 75 years ago, and adding this
countless host to the present human population of the globe.
Wherefore for all these things we account the whale immortal in his
species, however perishable in his individuality.
He swam the seas before the continents broke water. He once swam over the sight
of the Tures and Windsor Castle and the Kremlin. In Noah's flood, he despised
Noah's ark. And if ever the world is to be again flooded, like the Netherlands,
to kill off its rats, then the eternal whale will still survive. and rearing
upon the topmost crest of the equatorial flood, spout his froth defiance to the skies.